<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good old way and truth which the ancient Christians many ages and generations ago witnessed unto in the world from age to age, even from the dayes of Christ unto this very time, wherein the same doctrine, life and practice is witnessed unto by us who are in contempt called Quakers, through many tribulations, which our ancestors, the most ancient and true Christians that ever were upon the earth, sealed unto, with the loss of their lives and liberties, by which, in short, is fully manifested, in what is treated of herein, that the doctrine of the Quakers, in denying to swear any oath, and their refusing to pay tythes, and many other things they practise, was the doctrine and practise of the most famous and renowned Christians, both testified of in the Scriptures of truth, and the books of martyrs : also, a brief discovery of the ground and rise and tythes, manifesting them no Gospel-maintenance, but was testified against by the best and most ancient Christians many ages ago / written by ... Ambros Rigge.</title>
            <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12599599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12599599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 675:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good old way and truth which the ancient Christians many ages and generations ago witnessed unto in the world from age to age, even from the dayes of Christ unto this very time, wherein the same doctrine, life and practice is witnessed unto by us who are in contempt called Quakers, through many tribulations, which our ancestors, the most ancient and true Christians that ever were upon the earth, sealed unto, with the loss of their lives and liberties, by which, in short, is fully manifested, in what is treated of herein, that the doctrine of the Quakers, in denying to swear any oath, and their refusing to pay tythes, and many other things they practise, was the doctrine and practise of the most famous and renowned Christians, both testified of in the Scriptures of truth, and the books of martyrs : also, a brief discovery of the ground and rise and tythes, manifesting them no Gospel-maintenance, but was testified against by the best and most ancient Christians many ages ago / written by ... Ambros Rigge.</title>
                  <author>Rigge, Ambrose, 1635?-1705.</author>
                  <author>R. T. (Rebecca Travers), 1609-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Postscript," p. 34-39, signed R.T. [i.e. Rebecca Travers?]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letchford, Leonard.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Oaths.</term>
               <term>Tithes.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:1"/>
            <p>THE Good old VVay AND TRUTH Which the Ancient Chriſtians many Ages and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ago witneſſed unto in the World from Age to Age; even from the dayes of Chriſt unto this very time, wherein the ſame Doctrine, Life and Practice is witneſſed unto by us who are in contempt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> through many Tribulations.</p>
            <p>Which our Anceſtors, the moſt ancient and true Chriſtians that ever were upon the Earth, ſealed unto, with the loſs of their Lives and Liberties.</p>
            <p>By which, in ſhort, is fully manifeſted, in what is treated of herein, that the Doctrine of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> in denying to Swear any Oath, and their refuſing to pay Tythes, and many other things they practiſe, was the Doctrine and practiſe of the moſt Famous and renowned Chriſtians, both teſtified of in the Scriptures of Truth, and the Books of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>Alſo, A brief Diſcovery of the Ground and Riſe of Tythes; manifeſting them no Goſpel-Maintenance; but was teſtified againſt by the Beſt and moſt Ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians many Ages ago.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Branch ſprung from the Ancient Stock of</hi> David, <hi>which hath long been compaſſed about with wild Beaſts; but thorow the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies of the Lord yet remains alive; whoſe earthly name is</hi> Ambros Rigge.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>OH, Let not prejudice poſſeſs thy mind in reading this ſmall Treatiſe, for then thou wilt reap no benefit thereby; but let thy eye be ſingle to the Truth herein expreſſed, and thy whole body ſhall be full of Light; for God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſpected mens perſons in manifeſting his firm and ancient Truth, and Myſteries of Life, which were ever hid from the wiſe and prudent of the World, as it is at this day; yet not ſo hid, but that it is univerſally tendred to all without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, even from the King upon the Throne, unto the Begger upon the Dunghil; and therefore is mans deſtruction of himſelf, as God ſaid to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> becauſe man hath ſo much depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy upon his own wiſdom, and natural gifts and parts, that the things of the Spirit of God are fooliſhneſs unto him, as they were to the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and chief Prieſts of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the dayes of old, whom Chriſt called <hi>Blind-Guides,</hi> though they had natural learning enough, as <hi>Pilate</hi> who crucified Chriſt, had <hi>Latine, Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64135:3"/>
which any natural man may have, who doth not know the things of the Spirit of God, <hi>becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned:</hi> Oh, therefore, lean not upon thy natural wiſdom, for it will prove a broken Reed in the Day of the Lord, which haſteneth; but receive and obey the Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Spirit of God, which he in infinite Love hath given thee to profit withal; for that is the Talent that he will aſſuredly require of thee, with advantage, and happy for ever are they who can give an account of the improvement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64135:3"/>
            <head>The Good Old Way, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN every Age and Generation of the World ſince man had a being upon the Earth, God had a Seed, either inviſible in being, or viſible in manifeſtation, by and thorow which he manifeſted himſelf in his own way, time and manner, according to the good pleaſure of his Heavenly Will; which Way and manner, in every Age of the World, ſince ſin entred into the World, was contrary to the will and way of Mankind in the Fall; and therefore were they in whom God brought forth his Seed in all Ages, to give teſtimony in the World unto his Eternal Name and Truth, perſecuted, and made a prey upon by the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers, who was not acquainted with theſe ſecrets of the Lord, which was ever hid from the wiſe and prudent of the World; and therefore did the Jews and chief Prieſts with the Scribes agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Crucifie the Lord of Life, and after them many Heathen Emperors roſe up againſt his Members, and deſtroyed many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them for the Teſtimony of Jeſus and Word of God, as both the Scriptures of Truth, and the Hiſtories of the Ancient Chriſtians, which immediately ſucceeded the Apoſtles, doth large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plentifully witneſs, teſtifie and declare; ſo that ſince Mans Fall, <hi>He that was born after the Fleſh perſecuted him that was born af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 4. 29. even as it is manifeſt at this day, for the <hi>Enmity</hi> yet remaineth <hi>between the Seed of the Serpent, and the Seed of the Woman,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. and ſo will continue until the deſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things.</p>
            <p>Now in the 11th Moneth in the Year 1668/9 did the Word of the Lord come unto me, Saying, <hi>Write, and give a Teſtimony for my Name thereby, and ſpread it amongſt thoſe who have multiplied thine, and many others Sufferings, for my Name and Teſtimony, theſe ſeveral years laſt paſt, that they may all be left without excuſe when I call them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Judgement Seat, to give an account of the deeds done in their Bodies, who have not yet repented of their evil, but in ſecret have vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated themſelves, as that they have done me ſervice in perſecuting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64135:4"/>
them whom I have ſent to be Witneſſes for my Name and Truth in the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Words lay upon my ſpirit the moſt part of the aforeſaid Moneth, being willing to wait upon the Lord, that he might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſt his Will and Mind unto me, what I ſhould write, rather chuſing to continue in ſilence many years, then to ſet Pen to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to declare any thing which the Spirit of Truth would not ſeal unto; which burden of the Word of the Lord continued ſtill upon me, till I gave up thereunto: And upon the 21ſt day of the ſame Moneth, in the year aforeſaid, I begun to write, and the matter that was firſt laid upon me to write was concerning Swearing at all, for the denial of which, in obedience to the Command of Chriſt, I had ſuffered ſtrait and cloſe impriſonment well nigh ſeven years; beſides other great afflictions that have been added to my bonds by the hands of wicked men, in the ſaid time; all which I have been both made able and willing to bear for the Teſtimony of Jeſus and Word of God; not counting my liberty not life dear unto me, that I might finiſh my Teſtimony with joy, being counted worthy not onely to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for that ancient Doctrine, Faith and Practice, which the beſt and moſt ancient Chriſtians ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſered the loſs of their Liberties, and moſt of them their lives for; as hereafter I ſhall make appear.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, it is upon my ſpirit to give ſome Teſtimony againſt that abominable Oppreſſion of Tythes, under which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny groan at this day, it being never any inſtitution of Chriſt to his Miniſters, under the Goſpel; nor ever owned by the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſucceeding them, nor ever claimed as any Goſpel right for a thouſand years after Chriſt's dayes, till the midnight of Popery came over the Earth; in the which the ſeveral Popes ordered Tythes to be paid to the Mother Church.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, that the Oppoſers of Gods preſent Manifeſtation of this Way and Truth in this our day, (who have magnified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt thoſe whom God hath raiſed in the Power of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to revive the ancient Teſtimony of his Servants in the Earth) ſhould flatter themſelves in their rigorous proceedings againſt me, and many others at this day, for our conſtant obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, having no other thing to charge us withal, but concerning the Law of Chriſt: Now I ſay, leſt any who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64135:4"/>
againſt us herein, ſhould vindicate themſelves by or under colour or pretence of any Scripture given forth, either under the Firſt or Second Covenant, or the Law it ſelf by which they now proceed againſt us, which was never intended to take hold of the Innocent and let the Guilty go free.</p>
            <p>Now under the Law of the Firſt Covenant, while <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood in Covenant with God, they were commanded to ſwear by his Name in ſome Caſes, leſt they ſhould ſwear by falſe Gods and Idols, as was the manner of the Heathens in their dayes; as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſwore by the Life of <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and after them the <hi>Romans,</hi> by the Life or Fortune of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which was to neither of them any Command of God, for they then were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to him and his people.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to Swear by the Living God, <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and him ſhalt thou ſerve, and to him ſhalt thou cleave, and ſware by his Name,</hi> Deut. 10. 20.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> this was the Precept to <hi>Iſrael, Ye ſhall not ſteal, neither deal falſly, neither lye one to another; neither ſhalt thou profane the Name of thy God; I am the Lord,</hi> Levit. 19. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Numbers, If a man vow a vow unto the Lord, and ſwear an Oath to bind his Soul with a Bond, he ſhall not break his Bond, but do all that proceedeth out of his mouth,</hi> Numb. 30. 2.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their infancy was commanded to ſwear by the Lord, and to perform their Oaths unto him, by which they bound their Souls both to God, and one unto another, which in its day and time was well-pleaſing unto the Lord, they anſwering his requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings therein; but take notice by the way, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was but then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of outward obſervances, which made nothing perfect, and ſo it became them to ſwear by the Lord, as it becomes a child to ſuck; but not a man: for when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was grown up, <hi>(viz.)</hi> when Chriſt came, the Oath of God, who fulfilled the Law, and all the Commands therein, as they received him, and grew in Grace, and the knowledge of him, they put away childiſh things, and teſtified againſt all Oathes, and many other thing, which the Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, as being but typical, and Figures of good things to come, when the Subſtance of all theſe things was brought in, <hi>who came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it,</hi> as he himſelf teſtified to them that were zealous for the Law, and diſpiſed him, the Subſtance of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64135:5"/>
For Circumciſion was an expreſs Command of God to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being <hi>Jews</hi> outwardly, <hi>to them and their Seed for an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> Gen. 17. 13. for ſaith God, <hi>The uncircumciſed man-child whoſe fleſh of his foreskin is not circumciſed, that Soul ſhall be cut off from his people, he hath broken my Covenant,</hi> verſ. 14. this had a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more large extent then Swearing ever had, yet when Chriſt came, <hi>the end of the Law for righteouſneſs ſake to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,</hi> the Apoſtle told <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they were grown up, <hi>That if they were circumciſed Chriſt would profit them nothing,</hi> Gal. 5. 2. yet might Circumciſion have been more ſtrongly pleaded for; when <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> being God had commanded it to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to their Seed for an everlaſting Covenant, which he never did Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither under the Firſt nor Second Covenant; ſo the <hi>Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had more ground to withſtand <hi>Paul</hi> in crying down Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, then any hath to withſtand the People or God at this day, for denying Swearing: And under the Goſpel Swearing is more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely denied and forbidden by Chriſt and his Apoſtles then Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, being, but a little after Chriſt began to Preach to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> under the Second Covenant, by his own mouth, given in ſpecial charge to them then in being, <hi>Not to Swear at all,</hi> Matth. 5. 34, 35, 36, 37. and confirmed by the Apoſtle <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 5. 12. and never practiſed after by any of the Diſciples, as was Circumciſion; for <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards circumciſed <hi>Timothy:</hi> Therefore you who are ſo zealous for Swearing; why are not you ſo zealous for Circumciſion, which was more enjoyned in the Scripture then ever Swearing was, and with leſs Authority (under the Goſpel) denied?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And further, ſome pleads for Swearing, becauſe the holy men of old time did Swear,</hi> (viz.) Abraham, David <hi>and</hi> Solomon, Joſeph, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who gave forth the Law at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, ſaid unto <hi>Iſrael, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe unto you, like nnto me, him ſhall ye hear in all things; and it ſhall come to paſs, that whoſoever will not hear the voice of that Prophet, ſhall be cut off from among the People,</hi> Deut. 18. 18, 19. which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, was Chriſt, the end of the Law; and when God brought him forth into the World, he commanded <hi>Iſrael</hi> to hear him in all things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17. 5. who ſaid, <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was I am;</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Iſrael, Not to Swear at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64135:5"/>
The ſame Jeſus ſaid, that he was greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> Mat. 12. 41, 42. and was Davids Lord, and by him God ſpake to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was and is to be heard and obeyed in all things; yea, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall break one of the leaſt of his Commandments, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven; but whoſoever ſhall do, and teach them, ſhall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matth. 5. 19. by which, all you Swearing Teachers, and Swearers contrary to the poſitive Command of Chriſt and the Apoſtle, without any exception, may read your portion; for they who love Chriſt, both keep his Commandment, and teach others ſo to do.</p>
            <p>For where Chriſt intended any exception in changing of the Law, in what it had commanded, he plainly expreſſed it; as in <hi>Matthew,</hi> where it was ſaid that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuffered a man that would put away his wife <hi>to give her a Writing of Divorcement, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 5. 31. but ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I ſay unto you, whoſoever ſhall put away his wife, ſaving for the cauſe of Fornication,</hi> verſ. 31. [Mark] ſaving for the cauſe of Fornication; where Chriſt plainly expreſſeth the exception when he intended it: And at the 28th verſe Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the exception again when he intended it, <hi>(i. e.) Whoſoever ſhall look upon a woman to luſt after her,</hi> [mark] to luſt after her, <hi>hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart;</hi> ſo it is plain, that when Chriſt intended any exception in changing the Law, he did not leave his work imperfect for vain man after him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie.</p>
            <p>And immediately after this, in the ſame Chapter, Chriſt poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commands, without any exception, his Diſciples and Followers, <hi>Not to ſwear at all; neither by Heaven; neither by the Earth; neither by</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>nor by the Head, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 5. 34, 35, 36.</p>
            <p>Now here is a plain change of the Law, which commanded <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> to ſwear by the Lord, by him who had all Power in Heaven and Earth given unto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18. that he might rule all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with a rod of Iron, who fulfilled the Law under which <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Solomon, David</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſware; ſo is their Swearing no plea for any under the Goſpel to immitate, but the contrary.</p>
            <p>But it is objected, <hi>That by thoſe of old time, Chriſt meant the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiters of the Law, who ſaid, If men ſwear Truth, it was no evil; but onely they were not to ſwear to that which was falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is anſwered, that this being an invention of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64135:6"/>
and no where ſo ſaid in the Scripture of Truth; It needs no other anſwer, but a denial; for by them of old time, is ſpoken of them by whom God ſpoke to <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Law; let the Greek Readers ſpeak if the word therein doth not imply ſo much.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Iſrael</hi> revolted from the Lord in their hearts, and yet kept the Form of Swearing, and ſaid, <hi>The Lord lived;</hi> yet the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though they ſay the Lord liveth, albeit they ſwear falſly,</hi> Jer. 1, 2, and 23. though no truer thing could be ſaid or ſworn unto, then that the Lord lived; yet after they ceaſed to walk with God in his Covenant made with them, but went into Adultery and Deceit, and perverted Judgement, and judged not the cauſe of the Fatherleſs, nor the right of the Widdow; and laſt of all, the wonderful horrible thing was committed in their Land, <hi>Their Prophets propheſted faſly, and their Prieſts bear rule by their means, and they loved to have it ſo; therefore ſaith the Lord, what will ye do in the end thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So though it was true that the Lord lived, yet he lived not in them who were in the aforeſaid Abominations; they held the Form, but were gone from the Power and Life; and ſo then it was a cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary thing with them to ſwear, even as it is now with the Apoſtate Chriſtians, who are now in the very ſame <hi>Horrible Abominations</hi> of Swearing, Lying, Killing, Stealing, and committing Adultery, their Prieſts bearing rule by their means, more like lords over Gods Heritage, then any Examples of the Flock, and the people loving to have it ſo; but what will ye do in the end thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But though</hi> Iſrael <hi>play the Harlot, yet let not</hi> Judah <hi>ſo offend: But come ye not to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>neither go ye up to</hi> Bethauan, <hi>nor Swear the Lord lives:</hi> And <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith, <hi>They that ſwear by the ſin of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, <hi>and ſaith, the God of</hi> Dan <hi>liveth, and the manner of</hi> Beerſheba <hi>liveth; even they ſhall fall and never riſe again,</hi> Amos 8. 14. but while <hi>Iſrael</hi> kept Covenant with God, as I ſaid before, they ſwore by the Name of the Lord in Truth and Righteouſneſs; but when they revolted they kept the Form, and ſwore without fear, and prophaned the Name of the Lord, and ſwore by the Heathen, by <hi>Malcam,</hi> and by the ſin of <hi>Samaria,</hi> which was no where war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted to them by God; even as the Apoſtate Chriſtians in ourage, ſwear now upon a Book, for which they have not the leaſt colour of Scripture, it being made up of divers Creatures, which was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64135:6"/>
never commanded to be ſworn by, either under the Firſt or Second Covenant, but forbidden.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Again, It is ſaid, the Apoſtle in the Epiſtle to the</hi> Hebrews <hi>allows of Swearing before a Magiſtrate, in theſe Words;</hi> For men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſwear by the greater, and an Oath for confirmation is to them an end of all ſtrife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which is replyed, that the Apoſtle there ſpoke, of men that were in ſtrife, and not of them who had learned of Chriſt, as is very clear and manifeſt from his words, both in that place, and alſo in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He had fed them with Milk, and not with Meat; for hitherto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet are ye able. For ye are carnal: for whereas there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions; are ye not carnal, and walk as men?</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 1, 2, 3. Now theſe are the carnal men that ſwear by the greater, of which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who were in ſtrife, and ſo had not learned Chriſt, who ends the Law in which the ſtrife is: here <hi>Paul</hi> makes a clear diſtinction to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> between men in ſtrife and ſwearing, and grown Chriſtians who had learned of Chriſt, and did abide in his Doctrine; in ſaying to the <hi>Hebrews, For men verily ſwear by the greater, &amp;c.</hi> [mark] men in ſtrife, and carnal; not you <hi>Hebrews:</hi> And again, <hi>An Oath for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to them;</hi> [mark] to them, (not to you) <hi>is an end of all ſtrife; For where envying and ſtrife is, there is contention, and every evil work,</hi> Jam. 3. 16.</p>
            <p>And there is no more ground given by the Apoſtle for the Saints to ſwear at all, by any Oath, from the words before mentioned, then there is ground from Chriſt's words to the Saints, to exerciſe lordſhip one over another, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 42. <hi>The Gentiles do ſo, &amp;c.</hi> Beſides, did not thoſe that uſed ſwearing in thoſe dayes, do it to put an end to all ſtrife? but is not Oathes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at this day where no ſtrife is? nay, are they not impoſed for the beginning of ſtrife? let the Righteous judge how far theſe who would be accounted Goſpel Profeſſors are fallen, that they are ſhort of the practiſe of thoſe who were carnal, and lived in ſtrife in dayes paſt.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> to confirm Chriſt's words, when he ſpoke to his Brethren, who had learned of Chriſt, and come out of the ſtrife, ſaying, <hi>Above all things, my Brethren, Swear not, neither
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64135:7"/>
by Heaven, nor Earth, nor any other Oath; but let your yea, be yea, and your nay, nay, leſt ye fall into condemnation,</hi> Jam. 5. 12. This he ſpoke without any exception, as Chriſt had done before to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples; ſo as it was the perfection of the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, not to ſwear falſly; ſo it was the perfection of the Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, not to ſwear at all.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But ſome have ſaid, that it is vain ſwearing that Chriſt, and the Apoſtle</hi> James <hi>forbad, in ordinary communication, and not ſwearing in Courts of Judicature, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ſo, then Chriſt did not more then what the Law had done before, which is high preſumption againſt God to ſay; for the Law poſſitively forbad all vain and falſe ſwearing whatſoever, though it made nothing perfect; <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his Name in vain,</hi> Exod. 20. 7. This ſhuts out all vain Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without any exception, before the better Hope was brought in, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 19. which was Chriſt in them the hope of glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 27. who was and is the Miniſter of a better Covenant then that which commanded Swearing, which was eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 6. So the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of Neceſſity a change of the Law, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 12. and Chriſt did not onely change that part of the Law which appertained to ſwearing, but divers other clauſes and ſayings thereof. As firſt, that of Circumciſion, which the Law ſtrictly commanded, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 2. Secondly, Love to Enemies, which the Law commanded to hate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 53. Thirdly, Overcoming evil with good, &amp;c whereas the Law commanded to take Eye for Eye, and Tooth for Tooth, &amp;c. and many other inſtances which I might produce; yet he came not to deſtroy the Law but to fulfil it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 17. as the Jews who upheld ſwearing, and haring of Enemies after Chriſt came, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him withal, even as the Apoſtate Chriſtians now charges his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers who abide to his Doctrine, and dare not ſwear at all) to be Deſtroyers of the Law, and Contemners of Magiſtracy, and bringers in of new Doctrine. <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 19. which the ſame ſpirit in the <hi>dayes</hi> of old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon him and them whom God raiſed up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dayes to preach Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins by Jeſus Chriſt; who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Marvel not, my Brethren, if the World hate you:</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 13. <hi>For it hated me before it hated you; and the Servant is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64135:7"/>
not greater then his Lord, &amp;c.</hi> John 15. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Again, its ſaid</hi> Paul <hi>ſwore from that Scripture,</hi> I proteſt before God, &amp;c. <hi>and in ſaying,</hi> I call God to witneſs; <hi>which is ſaid to be an Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to the firſt, it is an intruſion of the Tranſlation, It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither in the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies, nor in the <hi>Latine,</hi> nor ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Copies.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, that he calls God to witneſs, is no Oath, but an earneſt atteſtation; for an Oath is that whereby ſomething is ſworn by; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to ſwear by the Lord in <hi>Truth, Judgement</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> and calling God to witneſs is no more, then to ſay, I ſpeak in the preſence of God, who knows the hearts and thoughts of all men, and is no formal Oath, neither under the Law nor Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any command more full in either Law or Goſpel, then Chriſt's Command to his Diſciples, not to ſwear at all by any Oath, without any exception, being ſeconded by the Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to his Brethren, as I ſaid before, enjoyning them earneſtly, above all things, not to ſwear by any thing either in Heaven or Earth, leſt they fell into condemnation, which Commands were binding to all both then preſent, and the ſucceeding Saints and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſeveral hundred years after Chriſt aſcended to the Father, and the Apoſtles Teſtimony was finiſhed in the World: yea, the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians many years after their dayes, kept the Doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> teſtifying to their death againſt the Heathen Emperors, who would have compelled them to Swear, affirming it a ſpecial mark and character of a Chriſtian, from Chriſt's words, not to ſwear at all, as ſhall be made evident anon.</p>
            <p>By all which it will manifeſtly appear, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> denial of all Swearing is no New Doctrine, but the renewing of that which was commanded and practiſed by the beſt of Chriſtians above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years ago, and continued in force and practice many hundred years, even till the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that <hi>John</hi> ſpoke of in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> got up and made war with the Witneſſes, and with the Saints, and overcame them that kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus and Word of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 7. and then the power of Darkneſs came over the Earth, which ſet up Swearing, contrary to Chriſt's Commands,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64135:8"/>
under which many of the ancient Chriſtians ſuffered cruel Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for ſtanding faithfull Witneſſes for the Name of the Lord in the Earth, and for denying to ſwear at all to thoſe under whom they were; as a cloud of Witneſſes might be brought out af the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtories of them that denied all Swearing in divers Ages; onely for brevity I ſhall inſtance a few.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who was, as its ſaid, <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciple, and had been a Chriſtian Eighty ſix years, when he came to ſuffer Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Proconſul requiring him to ſwear By the Emperors good Fortune, and By <hi>Caeſars</hi> Proſperity, <hi>(Irenius lib. 3. cap.</hi> 1.) which was the Cuſtom of the <hi>Romans</hi> at that time, and divers Heathen Emperors to ſet up their Images to be worſhipped, and their Perſons to be Sworn by; but <hi>Polycarpus</hi> denied, and ſaid, he was a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and would ſhew forth the Doctrine of Chriſtianity, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the ſame, if the Proconſul would appoint a day to hear it; ſo <hi>Polycarpus</hi> refuſed to Swear, and kept Chriſt's Doctrine, for which he was led away to be burned, being an old man, and full of dayes, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments vol. 1. fol.</hi> 55, 56, 57.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Baſiliades,</hi> an Officer, and afterwards a Martyr, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to Swear, affirmed plainly, that it was not lawfull for him to Swear, for that he was a Chriſtian: hence it appears that it was the proper mark of a Chriſtian, not to Swear. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol. 1. fol. 71. Euſeb. cap. 6. pag.</hi> 98.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the dayes of <hi>Domitius Nero,</hi> who began to reign about ſixty ſeven years after Chriſt, under whom was the Firſt of the Ten cruel Perſecutions of the Chriſtians, he cauſed the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of all ſorts to ſuffer; he commanded <hi>Rome</hi> to be ſet on fire in twelve places, and to avoid the infamy thereof, he accuſed the Chriſtians with it, and cauſed them to be put to death. After him began <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperor to reign, who began the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the Chriſtians, who was a Blaſphemer of God, and an Idolater, in his dayes was <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt baniſhed into the Iſle of <hi>Patmos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperor, fearing the coming of Chriſt again, commanded, that all that could be found of the Stock of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Jury</hi> ſhould be put to death: The inquiſition was this, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thoſe they ſuſpected to be Chriſtians, to ſwear whether they were indeed Chriſtians or not; but the Chriſtians refuſed to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64135:8"/>
Swear, confeſſing that they were Chriſtians, and could not deny Chriſt nor his Doctrine; for which they were commanded to be put to death.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> or <hi>Lioniſts,</hi> whoſe names are ſo famous among the reformed Churches, and who are ſaid immediately to ſucceed the Apoſtles, and were the moſt ancient and true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, profeſſed it no way lawfull for a Chriſtian man to Swear: In defence of whom, in the very matter, Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, (De Succeſſ. cup</hi> 6.) late Biſhop of <hi>Armath,</hi> Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> pleaded their cauſe againſt the Papiſts and Jeſuits, who are Swearers, and Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Oathes.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The <hi>Plowman</hi> in his Complaint, which is ſo much eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, and commended in the Book of Martyrs, ſaith <q>Lord thou giveth us a Commandment of Truth, in bidding us ſay yea, yea, and nay, nay, and ſwear for nothing: thou giveſt us alſo a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of meekneſs, another of poorneſs; but, Lord, he that calls himſelf thy Vicar on Earth hath broken both theſe Commandments; for he maketh a Law to compel men to Swear, and by his Law he teacheth, that for a man to ſave his life may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear and Lye; and ſo, Lord, through comfort of him and his Laws, the people need readeth to Swear or Lye; nay, oft-times to forſwear themſelves; Lord, here is little truth, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>vol. 1. fol.</hi> 527.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, It is one of <hi>John Wickliffs</hi> Articles, whoſe Works were as much eſteemed by the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as diſpiſed by the Papiſts and their Clergy, having his bones taken up and burnt forty one years after his deceaſe; and his Books were alſo burned by the Papiſts; and this Article was condemned, with many other, by the Counſel of <hi>Conſtance:</hi> That all Oaths which be made for any Contract or civil Bargain between man and man be unlawfull: <hi>John Hus,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> were condemned for holding of <hi>John Wickliff</hi>'s opinions, <hi>Ex Actis Conſilij Con. ſtat. vol. 1. fol.</hi> 606.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>Walter Brute,</hi> a Teacher among the People of God, in the Age of Scorners called, <hi>The Devil's Servant,</hi> or <hi>Lollard,</hi> againſt whom the Pope and King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and the then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Biſhops, made ſo much ado to have the Name of Truth extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and the Profeſſors thereof cut off. This is <hi>Walter</hi>'s Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64135:9"/>
concerning Oathes; <q>I believe and obey the Doctrine of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and my Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, which teacheth that Chriſtian men, in the affirmation of Truth, ſhould paſs the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees of the old Teſtament, or elſe he excludeth them from the Kingdom of Heaven; for he ſaith, Except your righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees ye cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: And as concerning Oathes, he ſaith, It hath been ſaid of old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform thoſe things unto the Lord thou knoweſt; But I ſay unto you, thou ſhalt not Swear at all, neither by Heaven, nor by the Earth; but let your communication be yea, yea, and nay, nay, for whatſoever is more then theſe cometh of evil: Therefore as the Perfection of the ancient men of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not to forſwear themſelves; ſo the Perfection of a Chriſtian man is not to Swear at all; becauſe he is ſo commanded of Chriſt, whoſe Commands in no wiſe muſt be broken; although the City of <hi>Rome</hi> is contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt.</q> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol. 1. fol. 653. Rich.</hi> 2d's days.</p>
            <p>Eightly, <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> who was a Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of whom much is ſaid in the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory; he blameth them greatly that brought forth a Book to ſwear upon; charging his Clerks, that in no wiſe, they conſtrained any body to Swear, whether they think a man ſweareth true or falſe, ſaying. <hi>It is a ſin to Swear well, &amp;c.</hi> Acts and Mon. vol. 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 701, 702.</p>
            <p>Ninethly, <hi>Jerome,</hi> who was an ancient Father and Teacher in the Church, whom all the Proteſtants owned, upon that place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 37. and <hi>James</hi> 5. 12. theſe were his words, <hi>It was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted under the Law to the Jews, as being tender, and as it were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, that they might offer Sacrifices to God, leſt they ſhould ſacrifice to Idols; ſo they might ſwear by God, not that it was rightfull ſo to do, but becauſe it was better to ſwear by God, then by falſe gods and Devils; but the great Evangeliſt admits not of an Oath, ſince every true ſaying is equal thereunto, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, In like manner doth <hi>Theophiliſt,</hi> an ancient Father of the Church, whom the Proteſtants own, and have often cited his Doctrine, for proof upon the place in controverſie, ſaith, <hi>Learn hence that under the Law it was not evil for one to Swear;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64135:9"/>
but ſince the coming of Chriſt it is evil, as is Circumciſion, and in ſum, what ever is judicial; for it may become a child to ſuck, but not a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventh, And <hi>Ambroſs</hi> ſaith upon <hi>Pſalm 110. Let him then Swear that cannot repent of his Oath;</hi> and a little after the ſaid <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſs</hi> ſaith, <hi>Do not immitate him in ſwearing, whom you cannot immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in following;</hi> and indeed the principle ſolution given by him is, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Twelfth, Many other Saints and Martyrs I might inſtance at large, both in <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth's days, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome were burned, ſome cruelly handled, who ſaid, <hi>It was not lawfull to Swear in private Caſes. Vol. 1. pag. 896. Hen.</hi> 6. days.</p>
            <p>Thirteenth, In <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth dayes it is ſaid, That neither the Pope nor Prelates, neither any Ordinary can compel any man to ſwear by the Bible-book, or any Creature of God; for ſaith a Maſter of Divinity, <hi>It is not lawfull either to give or to take any Oath upon a Book; for every Book,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is nothing elſe but divers Creatures of which it is made: Therefore to ſwear upon a Book, is to ſwear by Creatures, and this ſwearing is ever unlawfull.</hi> Acts and Mon. vol. 1. fol. 701.</p>
            <p>It would melt any tender heart to hear of the Cruelties and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which that Blood-thirſty ſpirit invented to deſtroy the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of thoſe who kept the Commands of Chriſt, and could not be forced to ſwear by all the Cruelties that the power of darkneſs, either in <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth's dayes, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth's dayes, <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds, or Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes could invent to torment their Bodies withal, which was not a few, as may be ſeen upon record at this day in the firſt, ſecond and third Volums of the Books of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>But they who loved Chriſt, and kept his Commands, in thoſe dayes had power and ſtrength given them to endure what ever the Lord ſuffered wicked hands to inflict upon them, by which their Faith and Patience was fully tried and manifeſted; but after the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of their Adverſaries were full, the Lord brought ſwift and fore deſtruction upon them, divers manner of wayes, as a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their Blood and Cruelty, as may be read at large, in the latter end of the ſaid Books: For God in every Age ſhewed his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere wrath againſt the Spirit of Perſecution about Worſhip and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64135:10"/>
unto him, <hi>(Gen.</hi> 3.) even from the dayes of wicked <hi>Cain</hi> unto this hour, that ſpirit is accurſed, and drove out from the preſence of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> where ever it appeareth at this day, even as it was in the dayes of <hi>Pharaoh, Saul, Nebuchadnezer, Herod, Pilate,</hi> and all the <hi>Chief Prieſts;</hi> and after them the wicked Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Kings; and after them the divers Popes and their Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſtly Rabble of Clergy, and all other, under what Name or Form ſoever at this day, where that ſpirit of Perſecution yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, the Curſe and Vengeance of the Almighty doth purſue it, where ever it goes; though God ſuffer long, as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the reſt, to vex <hi>Iſrael,</hi> till their iniquities was full: even ſo the Lord in theſe latter Ages hath ſuffered many to act much violence and wickedneſs againſt his Heritage, for their obedience to the Commands of his Son, and they who love him now keeps his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as they did in the dayes of old; for he ſaith unto his, <hi>If ye love me keep my Commandments,</hi> and his Commandments is not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous but joyous, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 2, 3, 4. and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>Hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his Commandments; for he that ſaith I know him, and keepeth not his Commandments, is a Lyar, and the Truth is not in him,</hi> 1 John 2. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>By all which it is more then manifeſt that the moſt ancient true and faithfull Chriſtians in their day and time gave a teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Swearing at all,</hi> and ſuffered for it, both under the Pope, and many Heathen Emperors; but they who would be accounted Chriſtians now, having got the power into their hands, are found in the ſame ſpirit of Perſecution, as they were in, under which the true Chriſtians alwayes ſuffered, and do act as furiouſly, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the power given them from above, as they did in dayes paſt, and no doubt would run as high as they did, in Burning, Hanging Gibbitting and Strangling, if they had the leaſt colour of Law to countenance them therein.</p>
            <p>By all which, let the ſober and honeſt hearted judge, whether the <hi>Quakers</hi> Doctrine of not Swearing be any new Doctrine or not? and whether our Sufferings this many years for our obedience to the Commands of Chriſt be not vindicated both by Chriſt, and all his Diſciples in their dayes, and by all the ancient Chriſtians before cited? and whether they, who now calls themſelves Chriſtians, are not far degenerated from the Life and Doctrine of Chriſtianity,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64135:10"/>
though they retain the name, and from the practice of the ancient Chriſtians, breaking Chriſt's Commands, and forcing others ſo to do, which in time will pull down the wrath of God upon their heads, if they repent not; <hi>For it is not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, that ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Matth. 7. 21. It is not the name of Chriſtianity, nor a Profeſſion of Chriſt's words recorded in the Scripture, that will hide you <hi>in the day of the Lord that haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, which ſhall burn as an Oven, wherein all the Proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble, and the day that cometh ſhall leave them neither Root nor Branch,</hi> Mal. 4. 1. <hi>the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it: For the Earth is filled with violence, and the Land mourns becauſe of Oathes;</hi> (Jer. 5.) <hi>and the Proud are counted happy, and they that work wickedneſs are ſet up, and they that tempt God are even delivered,</hi> Mal. 3. 15. <hi>and they that reprove Iniquity in the Gate are made a prey upon;</hi> for which God hath begun to viſit this Nation with his ſore Judgments, which will bring deſolation in the end to them who continue in the aforeſaid Abominations.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And furthermore, ſome wicked and malicious ſpirits have ſaid, we who are called Quakers will not ſware, becauſe we deſire to plot and contrine miſchief againſt the King and Government, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is altogether falſe and groundleſs, as many years experience will witneſs for us, who were never found plotting againſt any Government under which we have been, but have from time to time patiently born the rod of the wicked ſince we were a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and if we durſt break the Command of Chriſt to Swear any Oath, we ſhould as willingly ſwear obedience to the Power and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment under which we are, as any Oath that could be tendred us; this, for my own part I ſpeak heartily, willingly, and freely, without any reſerve of mind whatever; and if any ſhould have power given them to impriſon my body ſo long more as I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered here, if I would not conſent to hurt the Kings Perſon, or the perſon of any, I could as willingly ſuffer for the denial of that, as I have for my conſtant obedience and adhering to the Command of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> for the ſame Jeſus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me not to war with fleſh and blood, but to love my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and though I ſhould ſuffer five times more then I have done, I could never be brought to redeem my ſelf through the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64135:11"/>
of the perſon of another, though never ſo wicked and ungodly; for I know Vengeance is the Lords, and he will repay it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 19. and therefore have I committed my juſt and innocent cauſe unto him, who in every Age and Generation of the World recompenced <hi>Tribulation upon them that troubled his people, 2 Theſſ.</hi> 1. 6. though he ſpared ſome of them long, to ſee if his long ſuffering would lead them to repentance; but as they heardned their hearts againſt him, and his people, he manifeſtly appeared in many Judgments againſt them, to awaken them, as he hath done of late years againſt thoſe who have oppreſſed his Royal Seed in this Age, which he hath cauſed to ſpring up in his people, ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> which ſhall ſpread over the face of the Earth; yea, it is as eaſie to ſtop the courſe of the Sun from running his courſe, as a Giant, as to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth of the Seed of God; for he hath bleſſed it, and no inchantment ſhall prevail againſt it; yea, if all our bodies ſhould be deſtroyed in whom it is riſen, yet after us ſhall all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the Earth be bleſſed in it; for the more it is perſecuted, the more it grows; as when a Vine tree is cut, the more it is cut, the thicker it ſpreads; ſo doth the Truth at this day, as in Ages paſt, He was made perfect through Sufferings, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. 10. and he is the ſame ſtill, and will remain when all the wrath of man which works not the righteouſneſs of God ſhall have an end, and be no more; and therefore we cannot fear him that kills the body, and hath no more that he can do; but are taught both to love and fear him, who after he hath killed the body, hath power to caſt both into Hell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 28, 29. and therefore are we made a gazing ſtock to the World now, and have as little love from the world, as our fore-fathers had in dayes paſt, marvelling not why the world hateth us, ſeeing it hated him who is the Prince of Life, and condemned him to death as a Blaſphemer and a Deceiver, before it hated us, <hi>Luke 5. 21. Matth.</hi> 27. 63. for the Servant is not greater then his Lord; and it was the chief Prieſts that was the chief Murtherers of him, for they ſtirred up the Rulers to do it, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 13. which happily otherwiſe they would have dreaded; and ſo brought Innocent Blood upon their heads, and upon their Poſterity for ever.</p>
            <p>And who is it now that ſtirrs up the Rulers againſt his Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? Is it not the chief Prieſts, who both are, and ever were the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64135:11"/>
greateſt Enemies that he and his people had upon the Earth? who knows, that if people ſhould ceaſe from man, and follow Chriſt, and learn of him, down goes their Merchandize by which they maintain their Pride and Pomp, for the preſerving of which they will cry up any thing that will promote their trade, as hath been manifeſt in <hi>England</hi> within theſe late years; but God hath ſhaken his hand at their diſhoneſt gain, and is bringing contempt and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 12, 13. and they will become a by-word to many in Ages to come; and the Arm of Fleſh which they have ſo long truſted in ſhall wither before them; and the Lord will more and more gather his Sheep from their mouthes, that they ſhall not alwayes prey upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 10. the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it; and all their rage and madneſs ſhall but heap Coals of fire upon their own heads; for they have over-paſſed the deeds of the wicked in Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Whoring, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Couzening, Cheating, Pride, Luxury, Wantonneſs, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is Idolatry, a Generation of Vipers, ſtinging, and moſt grievouſly perſecuting all who will not put into their mouthes; I might fill a Volumn of their multiplied iniquities, which ever were the certain tokens, and fore-runners of deſolation and deſtruction, and the people thorow their evil example are overwhelmed in all manner of debauchery and uncleanneſs, even drinking in iniquity as the Ox doth water: Oh, was ever <hi>Sodom</hi> or <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſo over-grown with iniquity, as <hi>England</hi> now is? what will be the end of all theſe Abominations under which this Land mourns? Oh, that my head were as water, and mine eyes a Fountain to tears, that I might thorowly bemoan the Calamity of this people; for all fleſh hath corrupted his way before the Lord, their thoughts are the thoughts of vanity, and their works the works of iniquity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and miſery is in their wayes, and the way of peace they know not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 16, 17. Oh, repent, repent, and amend your wayes, for the Kingdom of God is at hand, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. 17. the Sword of the Almighty is drawn, it is fitted and furbiſhed for a mighty ſlaughter, and it ſhall wound the hairy ſcalp of every one that goeth in iniquity, <hi>Plalm</hi> 68. 21. Oh, therefore, return, return unto the Lord while he is near, and ſeek his face while he may be found; for he willeth not the death of a Sinner; therefore, if ye periſh, your deſtruction is of your ſelves.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64135:12"/>
               <head>A Brief Diſcovery of the entering in of Antichriſts and falſe Prophets, with their Marks and Fruits who inſtituted Swearing, contrary to Chriſt's Command, and many other things which now are, and for a long time have been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held contrary to the Scripture, and practice of the Saints of old.</head>
               <p>NOw you who call your ſelves Chriſtians, open your eyes, and ſee from whom you have derived Swearing upon a Book, which now you are ſo zealous for, that moſt of you calls it an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, let both Chriſt and the Apoſtles Teſtimonies be Witneſſes againſt you herein; and not onely them, but the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the beſt and moſt ancient Chriſtians, ſince their dayes, who under-went moſt grievous Sufferings, both from the hands of many Heathen Emperors ſeveral hundred years before there was a Pope; and after that <hi>Beaſt</hi> aroſe out of the Sea, (which then had flowed over the Earth) under whom many faithfull Martyrs ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their obedience to the Faith and Doctrine of Chriſt, who teſtified againſt Swearing, and many other abominable Idols, which that Beaſt had derived from the Heathens, againſt Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, all whoſe Teſtimonies ſtands as a Cloud of Witneſſes againſt you at this day, who are ſwearing upon Books, and laying your hands upon them, ſaying, So help me God; which, at the beſt was but invented by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Heathen Emperor, and after him by the Pope, from whom it is derived at furtheſt; and ſo condemns the <hi>Quakers</hi> to loſe all their Goods and Lands, and to lie in Priſon during the Kings pleaſure, onely becauſe they cannot deny Chriſt, nor his Commands, nor the practice of the Ancient Chriſtians many hundred years ago; though there is a witneſs in many of you that the people of God, whom you thus cruelly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, never plotted any miſchief againſt the King, or any man, nor ever countenanced any who would; ſo that there is not any people in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> that the King may more conſide in, then in the true born <hi>Quakers,</hi> who cannot betray the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64135:12"/>
Lord, nor the King; but they who are not faithfull to God and his Truth, can never be faithfull to the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here follows ſeveral inſtances of the Prieſts practices, for which they have no Scripture, but were inſtituted by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Biſhops of Rome.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>CLaudius Eſpontius</hi> a Popiſh Biſhop, at a Council held at <hi>Pyſoy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the year One thouſand five hundred, ordained, that Infant Baptiſm ſhould be received by tradition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it could not be proved by Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the firſt that ordained that Infants ſhould be Baptiſed, and have Godfathers and Godmothers; oh, what blaſpemous words hath Antichriſt brought in againſt God? how can theſe be God and Father, or God and Mother to the Child? and how can they promiſe and vow that the Child ſhall forſake the Devil and all his Works, and keep Gods holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all his dayes, when as the ſame men and women do believe before hand, that neither they themſelves, nor the child can ever perform theſe things? Is this Scriptural, or Papiſtical, anſwer Prieſts?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Pius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> built the firſt Temple after the Apoſtacy, in honour to the Virgin <hi>Prudentia;</hi> and ſince the Papiſts have built thouſands and conſecrated them, for which they have no Scripture, or example from Chriſt or any of the ancient Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> in the year Two hundred ſixty ſeven, divided both <hi>Rome,</hi> and all their Places into Pariſhes and Dioceſſes for Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Silveſter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ordained, that all Churches ſhould be Chriſtened and anointed with Oyl; and called them St <hi>Peter,</hi> St <hi>Paul,</hi> St <hi>Katherine,</hi> St <hi>Maudlen,</hi> St <hi>Hellen,</hi> St <hi>Dunſton,</hi> St <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> St <hi>Gregory,</hi> St <hi>Clement,</hi> St <hi>Giles, &amp;c.</hi> which ſuperſtitious names are upheld to this day, by thoſe who ſay they deny the Pope.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Clement,</hi> Biſhop, ordained Confirmation of Children, and ſaid none was perfect that wanted that; he alſo ordained, that Children ſhould be ſmore on the cheek, and ſigned with the ſign the Croſs.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64135:13"/>
7. At <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France</hi> they appointed holy dayes to encreaſe their Religion, (viz.) <hi>Chriſtmas, Candlemas, Lammas,</hi> which was never ordained nor conſecrated of Chriſt nor any of his Servants, who neither went to Maſs, nor obſerved any Maſs-Dayes, but kept Gods Command, who ſaid, <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour and do all that thou haſt to do, &amp;c.</hi> Exod. 20.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Boniface</hi> the fourth ordained <hi>Stephen, Innocent, Lawrence, Michael, Martin, John Baptiſt,</hi> and all the Saints dayes to be kept holy, againſt Gods command before cited; and the Apoſtle teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt ſuch Obſervations, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Gregory</hi> ordained, that Maſs, or ſhort prayer ſhould be ſaid over the Tombs of the Dead: Now Prieſts, ſee the original of your Prayers over the dead, and ſee if it be Apoſtolical, yea or nay?</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Gregory</hi> alſo ordained, that neither Fleſh, nor any thing that had affinity in it, as Cheeſe, Milk, Butter, Eggs ſhould be eaten on ſuch dayes as were Faſts; here came in that Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, commanding to abſtain from Meats, which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be received with thankſgiving, of them that believe and obey the Truth.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Sabinianus</hi> ordained, that People ſhould come together to hear Service, by ringing of Bells at certain hours.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>John</hi> the twenty ſecond, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ordained Bells to be tol'd three times a day; here was the original of your Bells and tolings, from the Popes Decrees.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Singing of Mattens at ſet times <hi>Hicrom</hi> appointed, as <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> and others ſay.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſecond commanded Prieſts to ſay them daily; and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilianus</hi> invented the decent tunes wherewith the Hyms be ſung, and joyned thereto the Organs, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> appointed that Lent ſhould be kept before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and added another week to it, which is called <hi>Quinqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſima;</hi> and alſo ordained Epiſtles and Goſpels; and <hi>Damaſus</hi> divided them as they are read at this day in the Reformed Churches ſo called.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> commanded that People ſhould ſtand at the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64135:13"/>
17. <hi>Higinus</hi> the nineth Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ordained the Commun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be celebrated three times a year.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Pius,</hi> about the year Four hundred and ſeven, after Chriſt, the tenth Biſhop, ordained, that <hi>Eaſter-</hi>day ſhould be kept on the Sunday.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> the ſeventeenth Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ordained Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards to be hallowed, and forbad marriage of Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Sextus</hi> the twenty fourth Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the year Two hundred and twenty after Chriſt, ordained the Prieſts to wear ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Garments, as Copes, and divers other things, in imitation of <hi>Aaron;</hi> and then came in Surplices; he commanded Images to be ſet up in Churches.</p>
               <p>Much more ſuch Trumpery might be inſtances too tedious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe, which is now upheld among the Proteſtants, ſo called, as great Ordinances of God, though ſuch things were never ordained by him in any Age of the World, but invented by the ſeveral Antichriſts which <hi>John</hi> ſaw entring into the World in his day, which are upheld by the falſe Prophets of our Age, without any ground or colour from that which they pretend to be their Rule <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Scriptures, who have either in matter or form erred from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth and the Scriptures in every thing relating to their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, profeſſing in words to know God, but in works denying him, being abominable and unclean, and to every good work a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A few words followeth concerning Tythes, manifeſting them no Goſpel-maintenance, but ſince Chriſt and the Apoſtle dayes invented by the Papiſts.</head>
               <p>TYthes were never commanded to be paid by the Lord to any but <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Law; neither was it ever payable, but by the Jews in the firſt Covenant, under the Levitical Prieſthood, out of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to ſuch Levites as had no part nor portion allotted them in the promiſed Land, the Tythe or Tenth part of the increaſe thereof was commanded to be given unto them by the Lord, for the Office of the Prieſthood, and for the ſervice of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64135:14"/>
Tabernacle, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 4. and the Levites out of the Tythes were to offer up to the Lord a Tenth part of the Tythes, and give it unto <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, for himſelf and his Sons, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45. 13. and no other portion had the Levitical Prieſts out of the Tythes, but the tenth of the tenths, for the reſt had the Levites that did ſerve at the Tabernacle, and it was alſo to relieve Strangers, Fatherleſs and Widows, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 29. So <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Tythes were not all given to the Prieſts, but the Poor was maintained out of it beſide, for there was not to be a Begger in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> here was the end for which it was at firſt inſtituted.</p>
               <p>But Chriſt the Everlaſting High-Prieſt being come, he changed that Prieſthood, which was but to continue until the time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. 10. and the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change of the Law, that took Tythes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 12. after which there was never any Command given by Chriſt to any of his Miniſters or Servants under the Second Covenant, either to take or receive Tythes of any people; and for Eight hundred years after Chriſt it was never impoſed upon the People, but they might give it to whom they would, at their own pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And the Maintenance which Chriſt allotted his Miniſters under the Goſpel is expreſſed in <hi>Luke,</hi> into whatſoever houſe they entred, to eat and drink ſuch things as were ſet before them, for the Labourer was worthy of his hire, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 7, 8. This is the hire the Miniſters of Chriſt are contented withal at this day; but the Miniſters of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt are not contented with their Allowance, nor the allowance of the Firſt Covenant, which ſhews that they are Miniſters of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for if they were, they would act according to one; but their Fruits plainly teſtifies to their faces, that they are Miniſters of Antichriſt, who have run when the Lord never ſent them, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 7. 16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Now ſome have pleaded for Tythes from</hi> Abraham's <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Tenth of the Spoils of the Kings, &amp;c. to</hi> Melchiſedeck, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Heb. 7. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was not Tythe of Lands increaſe, neither was it any Command of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but a free voluntary gift out of the Spoils he had taken in war; (but Mark) <hi>He was yet in the loyns of his Father when</hi> Melchiſedeck <hi>met him,</hi> Hebr 7. 10. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Goſpel Plea: So who would have Tythes from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64135:14"/>
muſt go and meet the Souldiers as they return from the Spoils of their Enemies, and receive the Tenth thereof at their hands, if they will give it them freely; for it is evident, that he who chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Prieſthood, and fulfilled the Law which commanded Tythes of Lands, ſprang out of <hi>Judah,</hi> of which Tribe <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake nothing concerning Prieſthood, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 13, 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And it is yet far more evident, for that after the ſimilitude of</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck <hi>their ariſeth another Prieſt,</hi> verſe 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who is not made after the Law of a carnal Commandment, but after the Power of an endleſs Life,</hi> verſe 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For there is verily a diſannulling of the Commandment going before,</hi> [mark] a diſannulling of the Commandment, that was carnal, where Tythes were included, <hi>for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs thereof,</hi> verſe 17, 18.</p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>it made nothing perfect, but the bringing of a better hope did, by which they drew nigh to God,</hi> verſe 19. which better hope was, <hi>Chriſt in them the hope of glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all which it is evident, that whoever receives or payes Tythes as any Legal right, denies Chriſt come in the Fleſh, and ſuch are the Antichriſts which the Scripture ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. and this is the reaſon why they who now witneſs him come in their Fleſh can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not uphold that Prieſthood which takes Tythes, knowing that he hath changed the Prieſthood, and the Law alſo, and not thorow covetouſneſs to ſave ſo much of our Eſtates, as ſome have falſely judged; for if we had no reaſon for the denial of Tythes, but to ſave our goods, we would aſſuredly pay them, knowing aforehand, if we do not pay them, we ſhall certainly loſe three times ſo much, at the beſt; therefore humane reaſon would not lead us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them upon that ſcore; but it is only in Conſcience towards God that we cannot pay them, knowing the Prieſthood changed, and the Law alſo that commanded them diſannull'd, as is ſaid above; land therefore, if we ſhould uphold that which Chriſt have diſannul'd, we ſhould be Antichriſts, like them, and wo would be our portion; And therefore we joyfully ſuffer the ſpoiling of our goods for the Name of Chriſt, and the hope that is ſet before us, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. 34. knowing that the Captain of our Salvation was made perfect thorow Sufferings, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               <p>And becauſe we could not deny him come in our Fleſh, have the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64135:15"/>
Chief Prieſt of our Age devoured much of our Subſtance, even beyond the bounds of humanity, and the Law by which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to claim it, which, at moſt, allows them but treble damages againſt them that refuſe to pay them, yet they have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with five times the value; nay, it would pierce any tender heart to hear of the havock and ſpoil they have made of our Bodies and Goods throughout this Nation, for our witneſſing Chriſt come in the Fleſh; appearing manifeſtly worſe then the <hi>Jews</hi> that ſcourged the Apoſtles of Chriſt, for they abated <hi>Paul</hi> one ſtripe of forty every time they whipped him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24. though their Law allotted forty ſtripes, yet they would not go to the rigour thereof: But theſe mercileſs Wolves have exceeded in cruelty, to the power they have had given them, all that ever I read of in any Age; for proof hereof I refer the Reader to a Book called, <hi>A Record of Sufferings for Tythes,</hi> wherein they are thorowly proved grievous Wolves indeed, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 29. who have exceeded the rigour of their own Laws many degrees, even to the utter undoing, as far as in them lies, of whole Families.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Some have pleaded the right of Tythes under the Goſpel, from theſe words, Ye pay Tythe of Mint, and Annis, and Commin, &amp;c. theſe things ought ye to have done, &amp;c.</hi> Matth. 23. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was ſpoken by Chriſt to the Scribes and Phariſees, who denied him, and upheld the firſt Prieſthood, and therefore he called them Blind-Guides, and cried many woes againſt them, for their Hypocriſie, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 16, 17. and ſeeing they did not own own him who fulfill'd the Law, they ought tythe their Mint and Annis, &amp;c. and ſo all thoſe who know not Chriſt the better hope brought into them to tythe their increaſe; but who ſo doth, muſt not aſſume the title of Chriſtians, for they can never be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Jure Divino</hi> by any under the Second Covenant; I ſuppoſe the Tythe-mongers have been aſhamed of that plea ſeveral years.</p>
               <p>Therefore let us come to their plea <hi>Jure Humano,</hi> which is their main Prop or Pillar; they ſay, by the Law of man, <hi>They have as good right to the Tenth part, as the Owner hath to the Nine parts, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is much like the <hi>Jews</hi> plea againſt Chriſt, to take away his life, <hi>John</hi> 19. 7. becauſe they had a Law ſo to do, which made them bold and impudent, not regarding the evil they did in executing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64135:15"/>
their Law, when it turned againſt Chriſt and his followers, neither would their Law they were ſo zealous for, defend them from the ſtroke of Gods terrible vengeance, which after they had filled up the meaſure of their Iniquity, came upon them and their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, though they were ſuffered to reign long over the Heritage of God.</p>
               <p>But let theſe Tythe-mongers tell us, who firſt invented this Tythe to Prieſts ſince Chriſt? and if they can clear the Pope of it, and deduct it from the Scriptures, or the ancient Chriſtians, let them; and then they will have ſome colour of Chriſtianity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Jure humano</hi> was the main plea in <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> time, by theſe tything temporiſing Prieſts, to uphold their pluralities and Tythes, though they could throw away the Common-prayer-Book at his Command, and ſilently ſuffer the people to want that which the ſame Prieſts now cries up as an Oracle and Ordinance of God, and Divine Service; for the reading of which they now wholly plead Tythe their due <hi>Jure humano,</hi> yet in thoſe dayes, when that which they now call Divine Service was rejected by them, they pleaded and ravened as much for the Fleece as they do now, though they ſuffered thouſands to periſh without that which they now threaten damnation to all who will not hear and receive; which if they had been true Shepherds, they would have laid down, not only their liberty and their Tythes, but their lives for their Flocks in thoſe dayes, rather then they ſhould have been led away by thoſe they now count Wolves, <hi>John</hi> 10. 11, 12, 13. but the Love of their Tythes and Pluralities which <hi>Oliver</hi> ſuffered them to enjoy, over-ballanced their love to their Flocks: and no queſtion, if the Pope come and hold out the Maſs Book to them in one hand, with Tythes and large Revenues in the other, and promiſe, in accepting of the one, they ſhall enjoy the other, and for refuſal ſhall loſe both, theſe cunning Steers-men, that can alwayes ſail in the eye of the wind, will no doubt ſwallow this Pill with little or no difficulty alſo, and cry up the Maſs-Book for as Divine an Oracle, and Ordinance of God, as the Directory was with them in its day, or as the Common-Prayer now is with all its Rites and Ceremonies now in their eſteem; for then alſo they may plead for their Tythes <hi>Jure humano.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64135:16"/>
And they who formerly endured turning out, could ſilently ſuffer their Flocks to be devoured by them whom they counted Wolves, and durſt not openly declare againſt them, nor enter into their Synagogues and diſpute with them, as the manner of <hi>Paul,</hi> and the true Miniſters of Chriſt was, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 16, 17, 18. for fear of loſs of liberty, or ſome other profit; if ſuch be not the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings that Chriſt ſpoke of, that flees before the Wolf, and leaves their ſheep, I know not any Hirelings at all; for was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Idolatry in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s dayes, and Divine-Service now? how was the nature and property of it altered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The main and principal Foundation of the Law of</hi> England <hi>is the Law of God,</hi> ſo ſays the Law-Book, <hi>Doctor and Student.</hi> cap. 2. pag. 4. in theſe words,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>There is a Law written in the heart of man, which is man cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in the Image of God, and this Law is alwayes good and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, ſtirring up the man to do that which is good, and abhor the evil; and therefore againſt this Law, (ſaith the Book) Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, Statute, Cuſtom may not prevail; and if any be brought againſt it, they are void, and againſt Juſtice, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo, then let all who hath the leaſt ſpark of reaſon left in them judge, whether it is not high preſumption againſt God, and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitted Prerogative and Royal-Law written in the hearts of his people, according to his Promiſe by the mouth of his holy Prophet <hi>Jerimiah? Jer,</hi> 31. 33. to ſet up mans Law above it, and force the execution thereof againſt it; for in the Second Covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God promiſed to write his Law in his peoples hearts, Tythes and their Law were aboliſhed, as is ſaid before; therefore Preſcription, Statute, and Cuſtom that is brought againſt the aforeſaid Royal-Law of God written in the heart, is void and againſt Juſtice by the aforeſaid Law-Book of <hi>England,</hi> which will not admit of <hi>Jure Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano</hi> to prevail againſt <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64135:16"/>
               <head>Here followeth ſeveral Preſidents of the Ancient Chriſtians, ſome in the Apoſtles dayes, and ſome ſince, who had no Tythes from the People, who gave Teſtimony againſt them that did require them.</head>
               <p>IN the Churches of <hi>Antioch, Galatia</hi> and <hi>Corinth</hi> the Saints poſſeſſed every man his own eſtate, where the Apoſtle ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a weekly offering of the Saints, that every man might offer free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of what God had bleſſed him withal, which was put in the hands of Deacons for the maintenance of the poor, and other neceſſary uſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 29. for Chriſt having in <hi>Luke</hi> 10. allotted their Miniſters their Maintenance, they were contented with it; and when they returned to him again, they could ſay they had no want; but then they lived not in pride, nor fulneſs of bread, nor went in long Robes, nor maintained their Wives in pride and exceſs, as the men of our Age do; for ſuch Chriſt never ſent in any Age; for they were not Lord Biſhops, nor call'd of men Maſters, but were Patterns and Examples to the Flock, and and ſaid to the Diſciples and Brethren, <hi>Be ye Followers of us, even as we are of Chriſt;</hi> but now if people ſhould follow none, but they that are Followers of Chriſt, the Tythe-mongers would have none at all.</p>
               <p>But the aforeſaid contribution continned amongſt the Ancient Chriſtians about Three hundred years till the great Perſecution un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Maximinian</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> witneſſeth, and ſo doth <hi>Turtulian, Origen, Cyprian,</hi> and others, here was not Tythes ſo much as ſpoken to of the Chriſtian Miniſters, but they did abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and having food and rayment they were therewith content.</p>
               <p>After which time ſome Lands were given to the Church, but <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <q>It is not lawfull for any Miniſter to poſſeſs Lands, given to the Church, to his own uſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> alſo teſtified the ſame, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how the Church maintaineth many poor, and that her own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences was full of frugality, and her diet ſparing and plain, <hi>Cyprian
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64135:17"/>
Epiſt.</hi> 27, 34, 36. <hi>Proſper</hi> alſo ſaith, <q>That a Miniſter able to live of himſelf, ought not to deſire any thing of the people, and he that receiveth it, doth it not without great ſin. </q>And the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> in their fruitfull and Chriſtian Exhortation to Kings and Princes, to ſtir them up to zeal for the Goſpel, in many Articles againſt the Clergy of their Antichriſtian Practiſes: In the fifteenth Article againſt them, they ſay thus, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That they receive Tythes of men, and will of right have them, and preach, and ſay, that men are bound to give them Tythes, and therein they ſay falſly; for they cannot prove by the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt commanded it, and his Diſciples warned no man ſo to do, neither did themſelves ſo receive them; but although in the Old-Teſtament it were commanded to give Tythes; yet it cannot thereby be proved, that Chriſtian men are bound thereunto; for this precept of the Old-Teſtament had an end in the firſt year of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, like as the precept of Circumciſion; wherefore, Beloved, conſider, and ſee how your Biſhops ſeduce you with things that have no proof; Chriſt ſaid in the 11th of <hi>Luke, Give Alms of thoſe things that remain,</hi> but he ſaid not, Give the Tenth of the Goods ye poſſeſs, &amp;c. <hi>Acts and</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Mon. vol. 1. fol. 860. Col.</hi> 2. in <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. dayes.</p>
               <p>But the firſt that reſtrained peoples freedom in this kind, was the Council under Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, <hi>Anno</hi> 1180. by whoſe time much Wickedneſs and Idolatry was crept in among them, as Hiſtory relates.</p>
               <p>But the moſt ſtricteſt decree was made at the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> under Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth, about the year 1560. they command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tythes to be paid under the penalties of Excommunication. About the years 800, 900, and 1000. and after, Tythes were called the Lord's Goods: So here was the riſe of Prieſts Tythes which for many hundred years they held <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> as they ſaid, which ever ſince they have exacted againſt the Law of God and right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and have not only robbed God, but the poor alſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is every Pariſh forced, to keep the poor from ſtarving, unto whom (if any) the Tythes do moſt properly belong; and yet though the Prieſts go away with the Tythes, it is very hard, in many places, to get them to contribute any thing to the Poor-Tax, manifeſting their Charity far ſhort of the Levitical Prieſts, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64135:17"/>
formerly out of the Tythes maintained the Widows and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, &amp;c. and conſequently far beneath the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: And furthermore, did ever any, either of the Levites or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel ſue any people at Law, that ſeparated from them, for Maintenance? nay, was ever ſuch inhumane actions known from the worſt of the Merchants of <hi>Babylon</hi> (let Hiſtory teſtifie) as to tear four or five times ſo much as they pretend their due, from them who do not like their Wares, and troubles them for nothing; nay, <hi>Baalam,</hi> though he loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs; yet he durſt not take it, but theſe are not contented with three times ſo much, which modeſty would bluſh to appear in; if theſe be not the greedy dumb Dogs which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpoke of, which can never have enough, I know not where they are, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>The with-holding of theſe pretended dues, at fartheſt, is but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpaſs againſt them, and it is their manner often to pray to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d, to forgive them their treſpaſſes, as they forgive them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt them, &amp;c. Now let the honeſt hearted judge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they forgive ſuch as treſpaſs againſt them, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the utmoſt rigour of the Law againſt ſuch as treſpaſs againſt then, yea or nay? How do theſe men think to be forgiven of the Lord? <hi>For,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if ye forgive men their treſpaſſes, your Heavenly Father will forgive you your treſpaſſes; but if ye forgive not men their treſpaſſes, neither will your Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgive you your treſpaſſes,</hi> Matth. 6. 14, 15. And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord how often ſhall my Brother ſin againſt me, and I forgive him, till ſeven times?</hi> Jeſus ſaid unto him, <hi>I ſay not unto thee, until ſeven times, but until ſeventy times ſeven,</hi> Matth. 18. 21, 22. So if theſe Prieſts could really prove that Tythe was their due, the with-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them is but a treſpaſs committed againſt them once a year at fartheſt; now if Chriſt would not allow of <hi>Peter</hi>'s forgiving his Brother ſeven times, but would have him forgive him ſeventy times ſeven, which is Four hundred and ninety times; what kind of Chriſtians are they who take treble revenge at leaſt, and oftentimes five times for every treſpaſs againſt them? this is ſo far from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm, that <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> would bluſh at it. Thus far it was laid upon me to give this ſhort Teſtimony againſt this abominable Oppreſſion, under which many groans at this day, that if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ears of people might be opened, and that they may ſee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64135:18"/>
how they have been blinded with things that have no Foundation, nor colour from the Scripture; and they who pretend the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be their Rule, may ſee that they walk beſide their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Rule, in either paying or receiving Tythes as any Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; therefore are they juſtly condemned and reproved by their own Rule, which will for ever ſtand a witneſs againſt them, both in that, and all other ungodly practices by them upheld at this day, for which they have not the leaſt colour of Scripture to vindicate them therein.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ambros Rigge.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>I Could not let this little Book paſs without annexing hereunto ſome few of the <hi>Bonner</hi> like practiſes of <hi>Leonard Letchford,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Hurſt-Pierpoint,</hi> who calls himſelf a Goſpel-Miniſter, which within this ſeven years laſt paſt he hath done againſt <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros Rigge</hi> for his obedience unto the Commands of Chriſt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is expreſſed. And ſecondly, of the proceedings of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Letchford</hi> againſt <hi>Ambros</hi>'s wife, becauſe ſhe could not in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence pay him Tythe, for the cauſes aforeſaid, as knowing it no Goſpel right.</p>
               <p>To the firſt, it alwayes hath been the practice of the ſpirit of Antichriſt, the better to effect its miſchievous purpoſes, to deſtroy and root out the Flock of Chriſt's Fold; firſt to clothe them with Wolves skins, and then to ſet the Dogs and Lions to devour and tear them to pieces.</p>
               <p>Now in the year 1662, and ſince, this ſpirit hath manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the aforeſaid <hi>Letchford;</hi> for when by the ſpiritual Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon he could not at all defend himſelf, as a Miniſter of Chriſt ought to do, he ſtirred up the Rulers in <hi>Hurſt,</hi> aforeſaid, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aforehand that for Conſcience the ſaid <hi>Ambros</hi> could not ſwear, to tender him the Oath of Allegiance, on purpoſe to inſnare him, for the refuſal of which he was committed to <hi>Horſham</hi> Goal the 28th day of the 3d Moneth aforeſaid; after the ſaid <hi>Letchford</hi> had effected this, he, with <hi>George Vinter</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Cove-old,</hi> cloathed the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64135:18"/>
ſaid <hi>Ambros</hi> with a reproach, as though he had run away from his Wife and Children in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and had left them to the Pariſh; which when this report was ſpread, it was asked <hi>George Vinter,</hi> who formerly was ſaid to be a <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> man, out of what Town the ſaid <hi>Ambros</hi> run away; who before witneſs ſaid, out of the Town of <hi>Eagle,</hi> which after Examination proved an abominable Lye; for the beſt part of twenty perſons of the Town of <hi>Eagle</hi> in <hi>Loncolnſhire,</hi> with ſeveral Officers both of their Church and others, who had lived in the ſaid Town, ſome twenty ſome forty, ſome fifty years, and never knew any ſuch man as <hi>Ambros Rigge</hi> live there in all their time, as may appear by a Certificate given under their hands, yet to be ſeen; yet theſe two Prieſts by theſe and other abominable Lyes and aggravations, got the Judge, at the Aſſizes following, to condemn the ſaid <hi>Ambros</hi> in a praemunire, at which Aſſizes <hi>Letchford</hi> appeared in perſon as one of the fierceſt of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros</hi>'s Accuſars, ſaying, he would aggravate the matter, at which words the Judge reproved him, and ſtopt his mouth; ſo after he had got what he then ſaw was poſſible againſt <hi>Ambros,</hi> he afterwards ſtirred up the Magiſtrates and the Goaler to add as much affliction to his Bonds as he could; by the which <hi>R. Luckin,</hi> then Goaler, to whom he wrote many threatning Letters, if he would not be ſevere towards <hi>Ambros,</hi> and keep him cloſe; ſo that the ſaid <hi>Luckin</hi> ſaid, that they would hang <hi>Ambros</hi> if they could, and ſeeing it his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to act his will upon him, and ſeveral others in priſon with him for Conſcience ſake, called them into the Wards, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, in the firſt place, to deny them ſmall Beer, unleſs they would give ſix ſhillings a Kilderkin for that which was ſometimes worſe then water; and becauſe <hi>Ambros,</hi> and others, could not uphold that Oppreſſion, was forced to drink water well nigh a year and a half; &amp; to try <hi>Ambros</hi> further, <hi>Luckins</hi> turned him into the low Goal among the Fellons, and there kept him his own pleaſure; and in the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following, when the Froſt and Snow lay thick upon the ground, the Goaler ſhut up <hi>Ambros</hi> again in the middle Ward, and took away his Bed, and forced him to lie upon the Boords for many weeks together, being cloſe lockt up, and would hardly ſuffer his Friends to bring him food, and as difficult many times for him to get water to drink; in all which trials and exerciſes the Lords preſence was not wanting to him, which made all theſe trials ſeem joyous unto
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64135:19"/>
him; it was not long after but the ſaid Goaler died. After him came <hi>John Moorcock</hi> to have ſome rule, though but a Servant in the Priſon, unto whom <hi>L. Letchford</hi> wrote a Letter, to ſtir him up againſt the ſaid <hi>Ambros,</hi> giving the flattering titles of Maſter <hi>Moor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock,</hi> who being of as bad and wicked ſpirit as himſelf, was eaſily induced by him to cruelty; in anſwer to which the ſaid <hi>Moorcock,</hi> about the 8th hour at night, in the depth of the next Winter, made a mutiny in the Town of <hi>Horſham,</hi> pretending the <hi>Quakers</hi> had broke out of Priſon, and raiſed a great Company with Clubs and Staves, and brought them up to the upper Ward where <hi>Ambros</hi> was at work, and without any occaſion given them, they ſeiſed upon him, pulling and haling him down ſtairs into the lower Ward, among the Fellons, where <hi>Moorcock</hi> himſelf put great Irons upon him, and left him in that condition many dayes and nights, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo long as the ſaid <hi>Moorcock</hi> continued in any Office in the Priſon; and when <hi>Letchford</hi> ſaw that would not do his buſineſs, he writ a grievous Letter to the Sheriff againſt <hi>Ambros,</hi> and ſpurr'd up the Magiſtrates againſt him, who were more wiſe then to give much ear unto him, though he could never juſtly lay any thing to <hi>Ambros</hi>'s charge, that he had either wronged the King or any man upon the earth; but only becauſe he would not break the Command of Chriſt to Swear; whom the ſaid <hi>Letchford</hi> often threatned with the Gallows, both in word and writing, and ſought many wayes to bring it to paſs; but hitherto the Lord hath chained him by his mighty Power, glory and praiſe be unto his name forever.</p>
               <p>And when he ſaw that all theſe devices and ſtrategems failed him, he pretends to have Tythes due from <hi>Ambros</hi> his Wife, againſt whom he imployed ſeveral rude Bailiffs; and when they did not proſecute her to his mind, he turned Bailiff himſelf, and joyned himſelf to a rude, ſwearing, bruitiſh Fellow, who, with himſelf, purſued <hi>Ambros</hi> his wife, till they took her, who cauſed her to be ſet upon the Bailiffs Saddle, and with mocking and jearing ſent her along in the mans Saddle to <hi>Horſham</hi> Priſon to her Husband; and at the Aſſizes got two of his kindred to ſwear falſly againſt her, whereby he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved eight pounds due to him from her, as he pretended, for the levelling of which, he the ſaid <hi>Lechford,</hi> hearing that <hi>Ambros</hi> and his Wife had hired a Room or two, and had ſome Goods for their neceſſary uſe in <hi>Horſham,</hi> ſent four Bailiffs, who entred into the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64135:19"/>
ſaid Rooms in <hi>Leonard Letchfords</hi> name, with an Execution in the name of <hi>Mary Luxford,</hi> who brake, and ſpoiled, and robbed the ſaid <hi>Ambros Rigge</hi> of Goods to the value of thirty pounds; yea, they carried away <hi>Ambros</hi>'s proper goods, which he bought for his uſe in the Priſon ſeveral years before, leaving not ſo much as a Bed to lie upon in the Winter ſeaſon; which goods aforeſaid, <hi>Robert Ryde</hi> Bailiff of <hi>Horſham</hi> ſold, at his own price and time, of which he would never render any Account, though he was often required, and ſeveral times promiſed he would; but the laſt time he was ſent unto, he ſent word, that he muſt have more goods for <hi>Letchford</hi> from <hi>Ambros;</hi> and afterward one of <hi>Horſham</hi> asked <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros,</hi> if <hi>Letchford</hi> had not robbed him of more Goods? ſaying, that <hi>Letchford</hi> was heard to ſay, that he would never leave off till he had undone <hi>Ambros;</hi> which though the party was one of his own Judgment, could not but condemn him herein.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, this <hi>Letchford</hi> hearing that the King was like to take ſome pity of <hi>Ambros,</hi> with many others, who had ſuffered many years ſtrait &amp; cloſe impriſonment, having nothing to charge them with, but obedience to the Commands of Chriſt, he, with others, not unknown, ſtirred up all the power they could, and got ſeveral hands to ſign a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, repreſenting <hi>Ambros</hi> to the King, a turbulent Ring-leader of the Sect of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and a Stranger in the Country, and not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to have liberty, thinking thereby to ſtrengthen his Bonds by theſe aggravations. Oh, that all who had any hand in this wicked Return, may find repentance thereof before they go hence, leſt it ſtand recorded againſt them in the day of Account; for it was the ſame ſpirit that accuſed <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Felix, Acts</hi> 24. 5. who ſaid, they found him a peſtilent Fellow, a mover of Sedition among all the Jews throughout the World, and a Ring-leader of the Sect of the <hi>Nazarens:</hi> the ſame ſpirit alſo called the Lord of Life, the Prince of Devils; and the Servant is not greater then his Lord; for if they have called the Maſter of the Houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more them of his houſhold. And this Prieſt, <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> like, hath cauſed the Furnace to be heat ſeven times hotter, then for falſe Swearers, who is but to remain a year in Priſon; but ſeven years impriſonment is accounted too little by him, for thoſe who cannot Swear at all, to break the Command of Chriſt; good were it for ſuch Perſecutors of the Innocent, that their Cradles had been
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64135:20"/>
their Graves; for then had not the cry of Oppreſſion followed them to Judgement, which in every Age of the World was the overthrow of the Oppreſſors, and pulled down the Wrath of God upon their heads, and if they were to go into everlaſting puniſhment, in the dayes of Chriſt, that did not viſit and refreſh the leaſt of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in Priſon, what will become of them that ſends Robbers to take away the goods of the Servants of Chriſt which they provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſupply their wants in Priſon? ſuch actions is ſcarcely heard of among the Heathens: Is this the way to convince gainſayers? did ever either Chriſt or any of his Miniſters uſe this way of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the loſt Sheep of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though he had all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth given him, that he might rule all Nations with a Rod of Iron? were ever Priſons, Gibbets, Stocks, Fire or Faggot to reſtrain or deſtroy the Bodies of the worſt of Hereticks, ever uſed or commanded to be uſed by Chriſt or any of his Miniſters on Earth? you who ſo much pretend the Scripture to be your Rule; what Examples have you therein of theſe things from the Ancient and true Chriſtians? but is not the Heathen Kings and Emperors, both in the Scriptures, and the ſeveral Popes, and their Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Clergy, ſince the Scriptures were written, your patern for theſe things? If you could prove thoſe to be in Error whom you ſo falſly accuſe, the way that you take with them would but more harden them therein; for it is a great diſhonour to a Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to oppreſs and abuſe the worſt Infidel in the World.</p>
               <p>And have not you kept ſome of the Servants of Chriſt in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon well nigh ſeven years, whom you have judged Deceivers? now ſince their commitment and confinement, how often have you ſent your Miniſters to convince them? Is not your whole Flock of Clergy able to do it? If you had had the leaſt love to their Souls you would have travelled and laboured night and day, by ſound Doctrine and Arguments, to have put to ſilence the ignorance of the fooliſh and deceived, if you could have proved them ſuch; if you had warred with them with the Sword of the Spirit; <hi>viz. The Word of God,</hi> and have defended your ſelves by that, we ſhould have believed you had been ſent of God, and guided by his Spirit, but we ſee you are ſhort of the Papiſts, who are groſs Idolaters, for before they delivered thoſe they counted Hereticks to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Power to be puniſhed, they ſent their Prieſts often to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64135:20"/>
them, and to convince them by Arguments. From all theſe your proceedings we are bold to conclude, that if there were no more Tythes and great Benefices in your Pariſhes to be reaped, then there is at <hi>Horſham</hi> Goal, you would be as ſeldom ſeen there, as you were in the Priſon aforeſaid, and have as little care over your Flocks, as you have of them there. Oh, that you would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what you are a doing, before it be too late; for the Spirit of the Lord will not alwayes ſtrive with you; large hath been the day of your Viſitation, which you have moſt grievouſly abuſed: The <hi>Jews</hi> Chief Prieſts did think they had done well when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Servants of Chriſt, who had more colour of Scripture for what they did, then you have; therefore are ye more inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the Lord.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64135:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
